Guide to the North Carolina Public Interest Research Group records, 1970-1983 UA.31.08.0004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Public Interest Research Group records
1970-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Public Interest Research Group
UA.31.08.0004
5 Linear Feet
Contains the records of the North Carolina Public Interest Research Group, a social and environmental action student group formed in 1972 at Duke University. Types of materials include correspondence, minutes, agendas, reports, notes, fliers, pamphlets, newsletters, handbooks and financial materials. Major subjects include Duke University, student political activity, student movements, political campaigns, consumer advocacy, Durham, N.C., lobbying, environmental protection in North Carolina, and the North Carolina Public Interest Research Group. Materials range in date from 1970 to 1983. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
Transfer; 1984; 84-4
Transfer; 1975; 75-61
Historical Note
Since the 1960s, college students in North Carolina have worked on goals of justice, social equality, and wise use of natural resources. Despite their understanding and commitment to these ideals, students often found their efforts frustrated by unresponsiveness in government and by the constraints of their academic role. The two major limitations that students faced were the lack of expertise required to deal with increasingly complex social problems, and the difficulty of maintaining continuous involvement due to breaks in the academic year.
The North Carolina Public Interest Research Group (NCPIRG) was created to facilitate activism on North Carolina's campuses. NCPIRG was founded in fall of 1971 by a group of students at Duke University, after hearing a speech by consumer advocate Ralph Nader. Duke University acted as the first headquarters for NCPIRG. Organizing efforts at nearby University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and University of North Carolina at Greensboro were turned down by administrators and trustees. In spring of 1972, students from St. Andrews College successfully organized and joined NCPIRG. By 1976, Davidson College and Wake Forest University had also formed chapters.
NCPIRG was funded and controlled by member schools. Students contributed a portion of their student fees to support NCPIRG as a campus group. NCPIRGs used the fee collection system as a stable means of guaranteed support. But, since NCPIRG viewed mandatory fees by themselves as an unacceptable means of support, they chose to offer a refund period to students. The refund provides students with a choice and makes NCPIRG directly accountable to students. This refund system was at times exploited by anti-PIRG groups on campuses.
The State Board of Directors was the major decision-making body for NCPIRG. The State Board was responsible for hiring professional staff, allocating funds, and setting research and project priorities for the year. School delegates reported their activities and exchanged ideas with each other at State Board meetings. The State Board provided continuity in staffing and support from experienced professionals.
NCPIRGs focused on environmental, social and political concerns. Some of the campaign topics of early NCPIRGs were high utility rates, nuclear weapons and defense spending, the draft, pollution, fair renting policies, and recycling. Because all PIRG members were students, PIRGs also focused on student rights, such as voting while living on campus, earning a full refund for rent deposit, student financial aid, campus-area grocery prices, and banking interest rates. Some of the most notable projects of NCPIRGs were land use pattern investigations in the North Carolina mountains, lobbying for changes in a local expressway, and organizing citizen testimony before the North Carolina Utilities Commission. They also assisted in the formation of the Brown Lung Association and sponsored the Generic Drug Substitution Act in 1979.
The Duke University PIRG, the most active of the NCPIRG chapters during the 1970s and early 1980s, organized the following workshops and events: Labor and Medical Center Employee Unions (1979), Truth in Testing (1979), Free University (1979-1980), and supported the Duke Draft Coalition.
As of 2003, NCPIRG is active and headquartered in Chapel Hill, N.C. NCPIRG does not currently have student-body sponsored chapters at North Carolina colleges or universities.
Collection Overview
Contains the records of the North Carolina Public Interest Research Group, a social and environmental action student group formed in 1972 at Duke University. Types of materials include correspondence, minutes, agendas, reports, notes, fliers, pamphlets, newsletters, handbooks and financial materials. Organized into the following series: Series 1. North Carolina college and university chapters, 1970-1982; Series 2. NCPIRG statewide administration and activities, 1970-1982; Series 3. National administration and activities, 1974-1980.
Related Archival Materials note
Office of the Chancellor. Environmental Concerns Committee records.
University Archives, Duke University.
ECOS records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Small Collections: Environmental Center folder.
University Archives, Duke University.
Lobbying; Environmental protection -- North Carolina; Public interest -- Societies, etc.; Political campaigns -- North Carolina; Students -- Political activity; Student movements; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Consumer advocacy; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; North Carolina Public Interest Research Group; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; North Carolina Public Interest Research Group
- North Carolina college and university chapters, 1970-1982.
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains the records of NCPIRG campus groups at colleges and universities in North Carolina. Types of materials include correspondence, constitutions, bylaws, notes, and clippings. Clippings and correspondence reflect the attitudes and values of students on college campuses during the 1970s-1980s.
  - Appalachian State University (Box 1)
    - General establishment and correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Bennett College
    - General establishment, ca. 1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and notes, ca. 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Duke University
    - Establishment and administration materials
      - Constitution and bylaws, 1970 (Box 1)
      - History, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
      - Organizational materials, ca. 1977 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence and notes, 1971-1974, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - Meeting agendas, minutes, and notes, ca. 1973-1981 (Box 1)
      - General environmental concerns, ca. 1974 (Box 1)
      - Summer internships, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Campaigns
      - Utility rates and deposits, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
      - Beverage container recycling, 1974 (Box 1)
      - No Nukes/Kudzu Alliance, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Labor and Medical Center Employee Unions, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Truth in Testing, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Free University, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
      - Duke Draft Coalition, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
      - Nestle boycott, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Printed materials
      - Newsletter, ca. 1980 (Box 1)
      - Fliers, posters, and pamphlets, 1971-1977, 1978-1982 (Box 1)
      - Clippings, 1971-1973, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - West End Community Action Group
      - Grant proposals and correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
      - General meetings notes and fliers, ca. 1978-1981 (Box 1)
        Includes Phoenix festivals, Vista activities, and clippings
      - Newsletter, The West End Times, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Elon College
    - Establishment, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - General activities, 1975-1981 (Box 1)
    - Student papers, ca. 1976 (Box 1)
  - Guilford College
    - General materials, undated (Box 1)
  - Meredith College
    - General materials, 1973 (Box 1)
  - North Carolina State University
    - Establishment, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, ca. 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1976, undated (Box 1)
  - St. Andrews College
    - Establishment, ca. 1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and activities, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, ca. 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    - Establishment and history, 1974 (Box 1)
    - General materials, ca. 1974 (Box 1)
  - University of North Carolina at Charlotte
    - Establishment, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - General activities and notes, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - University of North Carolina at Greensboro
    - Constitution and bylaws, ca. 1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and activities, 1973-1986, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Greensboro office space, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1975-1982 (Box 1)
  - Wake Forest University
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
    - General activities and notes, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - Western Carolina University
    - General materials, 1976 (Box 1)
- NCPIRG statewide administration and activities, 1970-1982.
  Contains establishment, administration, and activities materials of North Carolina PIRGs. Includes articles and correspondence regarding student fees and PIRG funding, petitions, meeting minutes, agendas, and reports, and clippings.
  - General administration (Box 1)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1972 (Box 1)
      Also contains general establishment materials.
    - General history, ca. 1983 (Box 1)
    - NCPIRG contracts with colleges and universities, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Solicitation licenses, 1977-1982 (Box 2)
    - Annual reports, 1973, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Organizing a PIRG, ca. 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Funding a PIRG and collecting student dues, ca. 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Employment and Manpower trainees, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Campaigns, 1976-1979
    - Background materials, ca. 1979 (Box 2)
    - Student voter registration, correspondence and general materials, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Student voter registration, clippings, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Watauga County voter registration, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Anti-PIRG bill, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, agendas, reports, and correspondence of NCPIRG
    - Correspondence and notes, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, and reports, 1972-1973 Spring (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, and correspondence, 1973 Fall-1974 Spring (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, and correspondence, Summer 1974 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Clippings and other materials, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1976 January -1976 July (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1976 August-1977 March (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1977 March-1978 August (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, and correspondence, 1978 September-1979 April (Box 2)
    - Policy notebook, correspondence, other notes, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1979 August-1980 May (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1980 June-1981 April (Box 2)
    - Clippings and other materials, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, and correspondence, 1981 October-1982 June (Box 2)
    - Clippings and other materials, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Financial Materials
    - General financial materials, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - General financial materials, correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Budgets 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - General financial materials, correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Monthly reports, 1975 September-1976 September (Box 3)
    - General financial materials, correspondence, 1976 October-1978 February (Box 3)
    - General financial materials, correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - General financial materials, correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Audit summaries, 1973-1981 (Box 3)
    - Lobbying expenses, 1977-1981 (Box 3)
    - Budgets and notes, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - Printed materials, working papers, and reports
    - Davidson College, Urban Sociology course papers, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Fliers, 1978-1982 (Box 3)
    - Pamphlet layout, ca. 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - Canvasser's handbook, 1971 (Box 3)
    - NCPIRG Advocate, 1973-1981 (Box 3)
    - Outreach, 1978 (Box 3)
    - PIRG Perspectives column and press releases (Box 3)
    - Of the People, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - The Insider, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Research reports, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
    - Research reports, 1976-1981 (Box 3)
    - Clippings in support of NCPIRG, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
- National PIRG governance materials, 1973-1980.
  Contains materials relating to the national governance and organization of state PIRGs. Materials include records of PIRG representative networking and solidarity in political action.
  - Governing council materials, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and reports, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Oppositions to PIRGs, 1973-1977, [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Letters of endorsement, 1972-1980 (Box 3)
  - Governing council, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - National PIRG conference, Colorado, 1978 (Box 3)
  - National PIRG conference, Virginia, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1974-1980 (Box 3)